When I was about three or four years old,
عندما كنت في سن الثالثة أو الرابعة
I remember my mum reading a story to me
أتذكر أمي وهي تقرأ لي قصة
and my two big brothers,
ولأخواي الأكبر مني سنا
and I remember putting up my hands
وأتذكر وضعي يداي
to feel the page of the book,
لأتحسس صفحة الكتاب
to feel the picture they were discussing.
لأتحسس الصورة التي تتحدث عنها
And my mum said, "Darling,
فتقول لي أمي " دارلين،
remember that you can't see
تذكر أنه لا يمكنك أن ترى
and you can't feel the picture
ولا يمكنك الشعور بالصورة
and you can't feel the print on the page."
ولا إستشعار الطباعة عليها
And I thought to myself,
فقلت لنفسي،
"But that's what I want to do.
"ولكن هذا ما أريد القيام به.
I love stories. I want to read."
أنا أحب القصص. أريد أن اقرأ ".
Little did I know
ولم أكن أعلم
that I would be part of a technological revolution
أنني سأكون جزءا من ثورة تكنولوجية
that would make that dream come true.
ستجعل هذا الحلم حقيقة.
I was born premature by about 10 weeks,
ولدت قبل الأوان بحوالي 10 أسابيع،
which resulted in my blindness, some 64 years ago.
مما أدى بي الى العمى قبل 64 عاماً.
The condition is known as retrolental fibroplasia,
الشرط المعروف بالتنسج الليفي خلف العدسة،
and it's now very rare in the developed world.
والآن هو نادرجداً في هذا العالم المتقدم.
Little did I know, lying curled up
لم أكن أعرف،
in my prim baby humidicrib in 1948
في طفولتي في عام 1948
that I'd been born at the right place
أنني قد ولدت في المكان المناسب
and the right time,
و الوقت المناسب،
that I was in a country where I could participate
في بلد حيث يمكن أن أشارك أيضا
in the technological revolution.
في الثورة التكنولوجية.
There are 37 million totally blind people on our planet,
هناك 37 مليون شخص مكفوف على كوكبنا،
but those of us who've shared in the technological changes
لكن أولئك الذين قمت بمشاركتهم المتغيرات التكنولوجية
mainly come from North America, Europe,
ينحدرون أساسا من أمريكا الشمالية، وأوروبا،
Japan and other developed parts of the world.
اليابان وأجزاء أخرى متقدمة من العالم.
Computers have changed the lives of us all in this room
أجهزة الكمبيوتر غيرت حياتنا نحن في هذه القاعة
and around the world,
وفي جميع أنحاء العالم،
but I think they've changed the lives
ولكن أعتقد أنها غيرت حياة
of we blind people more than any other group.
المكفوفين أكثر من أي مجموعة أخرى.
And so I want to tell you about the interaction
ولهذا أريد أن أخبركم عن هذا التفاعل
between computer-based adaptive technology
بين التكنولوجيا المستندة على الكمبيوتر
and the many volunteers who helped me over the years
وكثير من المتطوعين الذين ساعدوني على مر السنين
to become the person I am today.
لأصبح ما أنا عليه اليوم.
It's an interaction between volunteers,
إنه تفاعل بين المتطوعين،
passionate inventors and technology,
المخترعين المتحمسين، والتكنولوجيا،
and it's a story that many other blind people could tell.
وهي قصة يمكن أن يسردها عليكم مكفوفون آخرون .
But let me tell you a bit about it today.
ولكن اسمحوا لي أن أخبركم القليل عنها اليوم.
When I was five, I went to school and I learned braille.
عندما كانت في الخامسة ، ذهبت إلى المدرسة وتعلمت طريقة برايل.
It's an ingenious system of six dots
إنه نظام مبتكر بست نقاط
that are punched into paper,
تُثقب على ورقة
and I can feel them with my fingers.
ليمكن لي أن أستشعرها بواسطة أصابعي.
In fact, I think they're putting up my grade six report.
في الواقع، أعتقد أنهم وضعوا تقرير الصف السادس الخاص بي.
I don't know where Julian Morrow got that from.
أنا لا أعرف من أين حصل عليها جوليان مورو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was pretty good in reading,
كنت جيدا جداً في القراءة،
but religion and musical appreciation needed more work.
ولكن الدين وتعلم الموسيقى بحاجة لجهد أكتر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When you leave the opera house,
عندما تغادر دار الأوبرا،
you'll find there's braille signage in the lifts.
ستجد هناك لافتات برايل في المصاعد.
Look for it. Have you noticed it?
ابحث عنها. هل لاحظت ذلك؟
I do. I look for it all the time.
نعم. وأراها طوال الوقت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I was at school,
عندما كنت في المدرسة،
the books were transcribed by transcribers,
يتم نسخ الكتب من قبل ناسخين,
voluntary people who punched one dot at a time
أناس متبرعون يثقبون نقطة واحدة في وقت واحد
so I'd have volumes to read,
وبالتالي لدي مخزون لأقرأه
and that had been going on, mainly by women,
وكانت تقوم بذلك بالأساس النساء،
since the late 19th century in this country,
منذ أواخر القرن التاسع عشر في هذا البلد،
but it was the only way I could read.
لكن كانت السبيل الوحيد حتى أستطيع القراءة.
When I was in high school,
عندما كنت في المدرسة الثانوية،
I got my first Philips reel-to-reel tape recorder,
حصلت على شرائط للتسجيل من نوع فيليبس
and tape recorders became my sort of pre-computer
وأصبحت آلة التسجيل نوع من الكمبيوتر
medium of learning.
المتوسط الحجم للتعلم.
I could have family and friends read me material,
كانت لدي عائلة وأصدقاء يقرؤون لي المواد
and I could then read it back
و عندها أمكنني إعادة القراءة
as many times as I needed.
عدة مرات كلما كنت في حاجة إلى ذلك.
And it brought me into contact
كذلك قد جعلتني في اتصال
with volunteers and helpers.
مع المتطوعين والمساعدين.
For example, when I studied at graduate school
على سبيل المثال، عندما درست في كلية الدراسات العليا
at Queen's University in Canada,
في جامعة كوينز بكندا،
the prisoners at the Collins Bay jail agreed to help me.
اتفق السجناء في سجن خليج كولينزعلى مساعدتي.
I gave them a tape recorder, and they read into it.
أعطيتهم شريط تسجيل ،وبدأوا يقرؤون فيه
As one of them said to me,
واحد منهم قال لي،
"Ron, we ain't going anywhere at the moment."
"رون، نحن لم نذهب إلى أي مكان في هذه اللحظة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But think of it. These men,
ولكن لنفكر في الأمر. هؤلاء الرجال،
who hadn't had the educational opportunities I'd had,
الذين لم يكن لديهم الفرص التعليمية التي حظيت بها
helped me gain post-graduate qualifications in law
ساعدوني على الحصول على مؤهلات عليا في القانون
by their dedicated help.
بمساعدتهم المتفانية.
Well, I went back and became an academic
حسنا، عدت وأصبحت أكاديمي
at Melbourne's Monash University,
في جامعة موناش في ملبورن،
and for those 25 years,
ولكل تلك السنوات 25،
tape recorders were everything to me.
الشرائط كانت كل شيء بالنسبة لي.
In fact, in my office in 1990,
في الواقع، في مكتبي في عام 1990،
I had 18 miles of tape.
كان لدي 18 ميلا من الأشرطة.
Students, family and friends all read me material.
الطلاب والأسرة والأصدقاء قرؤوا لي المواد.
Mrs. Lois Doery,
السيدة لويس دوري،
whom I later came to call my surrogate mum,
والتي أصبحت أناديها أمي البديلة,
read me many thousands of hours onto tape.
قرأت لي الالاف الساعات من الأشرطة
One of the reasons I agreed to give this talk today
واحد من الأسباب التي جعلتني أقدم هذه المحادثة اليوم
was that I was hoping that Lois would be here
كان أنني كنت آمل أن تكون لويس هنا
so I could introduce you to her and publicly thank her.
حتى أقدمها لكم وأشكرها هنا علانية.
But sadly, her health hasn't permitted her to come today.
ولكن للأسف، لم يُسمح لها أن تأتي اليوم نظراً لحالتها الصحية.
But I thank you here, Lois, from this platform.
ولكن أشكرك هنا ، لويس، من هذه المنصة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I saw my first Apple computer in 1984,
رأيت حاسوبي الأول أبل في عام 1984،
and I thought to myself,
وقلت لنفسي،
"This thing's got a glass screen, not much use to me."
"هذا الشيء له شاشة زجاجية، لن يصلح لي كثيرا ".
How very wrong I was.
وكم كنت مخطئا.
In 1987, in the month our eldest son Gerard was born,
في عام 1987، في الشهر الذي ولد فيه ابننا البكر جيرار،
I got my first blind computer,
حصلت على حاسوبي الخاص للمكفوفين ،
and it's actually here.
وهو في الواقع هنا.
See it up there?
هل ترونه إنه هنا؟
And you see it has no, what do you call it, no screen.
ترون أن ليس لديه، ما نسميها، الشاشة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a blind computer.
إنه كمبيوتر للمكفوفين.
It's a Keynote Gold 84k,
إنه كينوت الذهبي 84k
and the 84k stands for it had 84 kilobytes of memory.
و 84k تعني أن له ذاكرة 48 كيلوبايت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Don't laugh, it cost me 4,000 dollars at the time. (Laughter)
لا تضحكوا ،لقد كلفني 4 آلاف دولار وقتها. (ضحك)
I think there's more memory in my watch.
أعتقد أن لدى ساعتي ذاكرة أكبر.
It was invented by Russell Smith, a passionate inventor
لقد إخترعه راسل سميث، مخترع متحمس
in New Zealand who was trying to help blind people.
في نيوزيلند كان يحاول مساعدة المكفوفين.
Sadly, he died in a light plane crash in 2005,
ومن المحزن، أنه توفي في حادث تحطم طائرة صغيرة في عام 2005،
but his memory lives on in my heart.
ولكن ذكراه تعيش في قلبي.
It meant, for the first time,
يعني هذا ، أنه وللمرة الأولى،
I could read back what I had typed into it.
يمكنني قراءة ما قد أكتبه.
It had a speech synthesizer.
لقد كان تصنيعا صوتيا.
I'd written my first coauthored labor law book
فقد كتبت أول كتاب لي في قانون الشغل
on a typewriter in 1979 purely from memory.
على الآلة الكاتبة في عام 1979 من ذاكرتي الخالصة.
This now allowed me to read back what I'd written
هذا سمح لي الآن بأن اقرأ مرة أخرى ما كنت فد كتبته
and to enter the computer world,
وأن ألِج عالم الكمبيوتر،
even with its 84k of memory.
حتى مع ذاكرة بحجم 84 كيلو بايت.
In 1974, the great Ray Kurzweil, the American inventor,
في عام 1974، المخترع الأمريكي، راي كورزويل،
worked on building a machine that would scan books
عمل على تصنيع آلة النسخ الضوئي للكتب
and read them out in synthetic speech.
وقراءتها عن طريق التصنيع الصوتي.
Optical character recognition units then
وحدات التعرف الضوئي على الحروف
only operated usually on one font,
تعمل فقط عادة على خط واحد،
but by using charge-coupled device flatbed scanners
ولكن باستخدام جهاز اقتران الماسحات المسطحة
and speech synthesizers,
والتصنيع الصوتي،
he developed a machine that could read any font.
طور آلة تمكن من قراءة أي خط.
And his machine, which was as big as a washing machine,
و هذه الآلة التي كانت كبيرة مثل آلة الغسيل،
was launched on the 13th of January, 1976.
أُطلقت في الثالث عشر من يناير 1976.
I saw my first commercially available Kurzweil
رأيت أول كورزويل خاص بي
in March 1989, and it blew me away,
في مارس 1989، وقد أخذني بعيداً،
and in September 1989,
وفي سبتمبر 1989،
the month that my associate professorship
الشهر الذي كان منصبي كأستاذ مساعد
at Monash University was announced,
في جامعة موناش قد أعلن,
the law school got one, and I could use it.
حصلت الكلية على واحد ، وأمكنني استخدامه.
For the first time, I could read what I wanted to read
للمرة الأولى، إستطعت قراءة ماكنت اريد قراءته
by putting a book on the scanner.
عن طريق وضع كتاب على الماسح الضوئي.
I didn't have to be nice to people!
لم اعد مجبرا ان اكون لطيفا مع الناس!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I no longer would be censored.
لم أعد أخضع للرقابة.
For example, I was too shy then,
على سبيل المثال، كنت حينها خجولا جداً
and I'm actually too shy now, to ask anybody
وأنا فعلا ما زلت أخجل أن أطلب من أي شخص
to read me out loud sexually explicit material.
ان يقرأ لي المواد الجنسية الفاضحة بصوت عال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But, you know, I could pop a book on in the middle of the night, and --
ولكن، كما تعلمون،يمكنني أخذ كتاب في منتصف الليل، و--
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Now, the Kurzweil reader is simply
الآن، ببساطة قارئ كورزويل
a program on my laptop.
برنامج على حاسوبي المحمول.
That's what it's shrunk to.
وهذا ماتحول إليه.
And now I can scan the latest novel
والآن يمكنني ان اقوم بالمسح الضوئي لأية رواية
and not wait to get it into talking book libraries.
وعدم انتظار للحصول عليها من المكتبات.
I can keep up with my friends.
يمكنني المواكبة مع أصدقائي.
There are many people who have helped me in my life,
هناك الكثير من الناس الذين ساعدوني في حياتي،
and many that I haven't met.
ولم ألتق العديد منهم .
One is another American inventor Ted Henter.
واحد منهم المخترع الآخر الأمريكي تيد هنتر.
Ted was a motorcycle racer,
كان تيد متسابق للدراجات النارية،
but in 1978 he had a car accident and lost his sight,
لكن في عام 1978 تعرض لحادث سير وفقد بصره,
which is devastating if you're trying to ride motorbikes.
الشيء المدمر هو إذا حاولت ركوب الدراجات النارية.
He then turned to being a waterskier
ثم تحول حينها إلى راكب للأمواج
and was a champion disabled waterskier.
وكان بطل المعاقين في ركوب الأمواج .
But in 1989, he teamed up with Bill Joyce
ولكن في عام 1989، اشترك مع بيل جويس
to develop a program that would read out
لتطوير برنامج يستطيع أن يقرأ
what was on the computer screen
ما يوجد على شاشة الكمبيوتر
from the Net or from what was on the computer.
من الإنترنيت أو الكمبيوتر.
It's called JAWS, Job Access With Speech,
أطلق عليه جوس، "الوصول إلى الوظيفة بالكلام"،
and it sounds like this.
إنه يبدو هكذا
(JAWS speaking)
(جوس يتحدث)
Ron McCallum: Isn't that slow?
رون ماكالوم: ليس بهذا البطء؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You see, if I read like that, I'd fall asleep.
كما ترون، إذا قرأت بهذا الشكل، ستنامون
I slowed it down for you.
أنا أتباطأ أكثر منك.
I'm going to ask that we play it at the speed I read it.
سأحاول أن نشغله بنفس السرعة التي أقرأ بها
Can we play that one?
هل مستطيع أن نشغل هذا ؟
(JAWS speaking)
(جوس يتحدث)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
RM: You know, when you're marking student essays,
رون : هل تتذكرعندما كنت تصحح مقالات الطلاب
you want to get through them fairly quickly.
كنت تريد أن يحصل ذلك بسرعة.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
This technology that fascinated me in 1987
هذه التكنولوجيا التي سحرتني في عام 1987
is now on my iPhone and on yours as well.
الآن هي على هاتفي أي فون وعندكم كذلك.
But, you know, I find reading with machines
ولكن، كما تعلمون، أجد القراءة بآلالآت
a very lonely process.
عملية من غير رفيق.
I grew up with family, friends, reading to me,
لقد نشأت مع الأسرة والأصدقاء وهم يقرؤون لي،
and I loved the warmth and the breath
وأنا أحب الدفء والنفس
and the closeness of people reading.
والقرب من الناس الذين يقرؤون.
Do you love being read to?
هل تحب أن أقرأها لك؟
And one of my most enduring memories
ومن ذكرياتي الراسخة لدي
is in 1999, Mary reading to me and the children
كانت في عام 1999، ماري تقرأ لي وللأطفال
down near Manly Beach
قرب شاطئ مانلي
"Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone."
"هاري بوتر وحجر الفيلسوف".
Isn't that a great book?
أليس هذا كتاباً عظيماً؟
I still love being close to someone reading to me.
أنا أحب أن أكون على مقربة من شخص يقرأ لي.
But I wouldn't give up the technology,
ولكن لن أتخلى عن التكنولوجيا،
because it's allowed me to lead a great life.
لأنها أتاحت لي فرصة عيش حياة رائعة.
Of course, talking books for the blind
بالطبع، الكتب الناطقة للمكفوفين
predated all this technology.
سبقت كل هذه التكنولوجيا.
After all, the long-playing record was developed
بعد كل شيء، تم تطوير سجل أقراص
in the early 1930s,
في أوائل الثلاثينات من القرن الماضي،
and now we put talking books on CDs
والآن علينا وضع الكتب المسموعة على الأقراص المدمجة
using the digital access system known as DAISY.
باستخدام نظام الوصول الرقمي المعروف باسم ديزي.
But when I'm reading with synthetic voices,
لكن عندما اقرأه مع الأصوات الاصطناعية،
I love to come home and read a racy novel
أحب أن أعود للمنزل وقراءة رواية مفعمة بالحيوية
with a real voice.
بصوت حقيقي.
Now there are still barriers
الآن لا تزال هناك حواجز
in front of we people with disabilities.
أمامنا نحن الأشخاص ذوي الإعاقة.
Many websites we can't read using JAWS
العديد من المواقع لا يمكننا قراءتها باستخدام تقنية جوس
and the other technologies.
وغيرها من التكنولوجيات.
Websites are often very visual,
المواقع غالباً ما تكون مرئية ،
and there are all these sorts of graphs
و فيها جميع الأنواع من الرسومات البيانية
that aren't labeled and buttons that aren't labeled,
غير المصنفة والأزرار غير المصنفة
and that's why the World Wide Web Consortium 3,
لهذا السبب اتحاد شبكة ويب العالمية 3،
known as W3C, has developed worldwide standards
المعروف باسم W3C، قد وضع معايير في جميع أنحاء العالم
for the Internet.
للاتصال بالإنترنت.
And we want all Internet users or Internet site owners
ونحن نريد من جميع مستخدمي الإنترنت أو أصحاب المواقع
to make their sites compatible so that
جعل هذه المواقع متوافقة حتى
we persons without vision can have a level playing field.
يكون لنا نحن الأشخاص المكفوفين تكافؤ معكم.
There are other barriers brought about by our laws.
وهناك حواجز أخرى أحدثتها قوانيننا.
For example, Australia,
على سبيل المثال، في أستراليا،
like about one third of the world's countries,
مثل حوالي ثلث بلدان العالم،
has copyright exceptions which allow books to be brailled
لها حقوق نشر إستتنائية تسمح أن تكون الكتب بطريقة برايل
or read for we blind persons.
ومقروءة للمكفوفين.
But those books can't travel across borders.
ولكن تلك الكتب لاتستطيع السفر عبر الحدود.
For example, in Spain, there are a 100,000
على سبيل المثال، في إسبانيا، هناك 100,000
accessible books in Spanish.
من الكتب المتاحة بالإسبانية.
In Argentina, there are 50,000.
في الأرجنتين، هناك 50,000.
In no other Latin American country
في بلدان أمريكا اللاتينية الأخرى
are there more than a couple of thousand.
هناك أكثر من بضعة آلاف.
But it's not legal to transport the books
ولكن غيرمسموح نقل هذه الكتب
from Spain to Latin America.
من إسبانيا إلى أمريكا اللاتينية.
There are hundreds of thousands of accessible books
وهناك مئات الآلاف من الكتب المتاحة
in the United States, Britain, Canada, Australia, etc.,
في الولايات المتحدة، وبريطانيا، وكندا، وأستراليا، إلخ.،
but they can't be transported to the 60 countries
إلا أنها لا يمكن أن تنقل إلى 60 بلدا
in our world where English is the first and the second language.
في عالمنا حيث اللغة الإنجليزية هي اللغة الأولى أو الثانية.
And remember I was telling you about Harry Potter.
وتذكروا ما كنت قد أخبرتكم عن هاري بوتر.
Well, because we can't transport books across borders,
حسنا، لأننا لا يمكننا نقل الكتب عبر الحدود،
there had to be separate versions read
يجب أن تكون هناك إصدارات متعددة للقراءة
in all the different English-speaking countries:
في جميع البلدان المختلفة الناطقة بالإنجليزية.
Britain, United States, Canada, Australia,
بريطانيا، أمريكا, وكندا، وأستراليا،
and New Zealand all had to have
و نيوزيلندا وجب أن يكون لديهم
separate readings of Harry Potter.
إصدارات منفصلة من هاري بوتر.
And that's why, next month in Morocco,
ولهذا السبب، الشهر المقبل في المغرب،
a meeting is taking place between all the countries.
سيعقد لقاء بين جميع الدول.
It's something that a group of countries
إنها مجموعة من االدول
and the World Blind Union are advocating,
إضافة إلى "الاتحاد العالمي للمكفوفين" تدعو ،
a cross-border treaty
إلى معاهدة عبرالحدود
so that if books are available under a copyright exception
حيث أنه إذا كانت هناك الكتب المتاحة بموجب استثناء حقوق النشر
and the other country has a copyright exception,
و بلد آخر له استثناء حقوق النشر،
we can transport those books across borders
يمكن نقل تلك الكتب عبر الحدود
and give life to people, particularly in developing countries,
وإحياء الناس ، لا سيما في البلدان النامية،
blind people who don't have the books to read.
حيت المكفوفين ليس لديهم الكتب لقراءتها.
I want that to happen.
أريد أن يحدث هذا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
My life has been extraordinarily blessed
قد منحت حياة رائعة
with marriage and children
وزواخ وأطفال
and certainly interesting work to do,
وبالتأكيد عملا مهما أقوم به ,
whether it be at the University of Sydney Law School,
سواء كان ذلك في كلية الحقوق بجامعة سيدني،
where I served a term as dean,
حيث عملت فترة كعميد،
or now as I sit on the United Nations Committee
أو الآن وأنا في "لجنة الأمم المتحدة"
on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, in Geneva.
لحقوق الأشخاص ذوي الإعاقة، في جنيف.
I've indeed been a very fortunate human being.
في الواقع لقد كنت إنسان محظوظ جداً.
I wonder what the future will hold.
وأتساءل ما الذي سيحصل مستقبلا.
The technology will advance even further,
سوف تتقدم التكنولوجيا أبعد من ذلك،
but I can still remember my mum saying, 60 years ago,
ولكن لا زلت أتذكر أمي وهي تقول ، قبل 60 عاماً،
"Remember, darling,
"تذكر، دارلين
you'll never be able to read the print with your fingers."
أنت لن تكون قادراً أبداً على قراءة الطباعة بأصابعك. "
I'm so glad that the interaction between braille transcribers,
وأنا سعيد للغاية أن التفاعل بين ناسخي برايل
volunteer readers and passionate inventors,
والقراء المتطوعين والمخترعين المتحمسين ،
has allowed this dream of reading to come true for me
سمح لحلم القراءة هذا أن يصبح حقيقة بالنسبة لي
and for blind people throughout the world.
وبالنسبة للأشخاص المكفوفين في جميع أنحاء العالم.
I'd like to thank my researcher Hannah Martin,
وأود أن أشكرالباحث مارتن هانا،
who is my slide clicker, who clicks the slides,
وهو ناقر الشرائح ، الذين يقوم بالنقر فوق الشرائح،
and my wife, Professor Mary Crock, who's the light of my life,
وزوجتي، أستاذة ماري كروك، التي هي نور حياتي،
is coming on to collect me.
لقد قدمت هنا لدعمي
I want to thank her too.
أريد أن اشكرها كثيرا.
I think I have to say goodbye now.
أعتقد أنه يجب أن أقول وداعا الآن.
Bless you. Thank you very much.
بارك الله فيكم. شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Yay! (Applause)
ياي! (تصفيق)
Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. (Applause)
حسنا. حسنا. حسنا. حسنا. حسنا. (تصفيق)